part 3 chapter 6.
The Chestnut Tree was almost empty.
A ray of sunlight slanting through a window fell on dusty tabletops
It was the lonely hour of 15.
A teeny music trickled from the telescreens.
Winston said in his usual corner, gazing into an empty glass.
Now and again he glanced up at a vast face which eyed him from the opposite wall.
BIG BROTHER IS WATCHING YOU, the captain said.
Unbidden, a waiter came and filled his glass up with Victory Gin, shaking into
it a few drops from another bottle with a quilt through the cork.
It was saccharin flavored with cloves, the specialty of the cafe
Winston was listening to the telescreen the present-only music was coming out of
it, but there was a possibility that at any moment there might be a special
bulletin from the Ministry of Peace.
The news from the African front was disquieting in the extreme.
On and off he had been worrying about it all day.
A Eurasian army (Oceania was at war with Eurasia: Oceania had always been at war
with Eurasia) was moving southward at a terrifying speed.
The midday bulletin had not mentioned any definite area, but it was probable
that already the mouth of the Congo was a battlefield razaville and Leopoldville were in danger.
One did not have to look at the map to see what it meant.
It was not merely a question of losing Central Africa: for the first time in the
whole war, the territory of Oceania itself was menaced.
A violent emotion, not fear exactly but a sort of undifferentiated excitement,
flared up in him, then faded again.
He stopped thinking about the war.
In these days he could never fix his mind on any one subject for more than a
few moments at a time.
He picked up his glass and drained it at a gulp.
As always the gin made him shudder and even Rich slightly.
The stuff was horrible.
The cloves and saccharin themselves disgusting enough in their sickly way,
could not disguise the flat oily smell; and what was worst of all was that the
smell of gin, which dwelt with him night and day, was inextricably mixed up in his
mind with the smell of those——— He never named them, even in his thoughts,
and so far as it was possible he never visualized them there was something that
he was half aware of, hovering close to his face, a smell that clung to his nostrils.
As the gin rose in him he belched through purple lips.
He had grown fatter since they released him, and had regained his old color
indeed, more than regained it. His features had thickened, the skin on nose
and cheekbones was coarsely read even the bald scalp was too deep a pink.
A waiter, again unbidden, brought the chessboard into the current issue of the
Times, with the page turned down at the chess problem.
Then, seeing that Winston's glass was empty, he brought the gin bottle and filled it.
There was no need to give orders. They knew his habits. The chessboard was
always waiting for him, his corner table was always reserved; even when the place
was full he had it to himself, since nobody cared to be seen sitting too close to him.
He never even bothered to count his drinks.
At irregular intervals they presented him with a dirty slip of paper which
they said was the bill, but he had the impression that they always undercharged
him. It would have made no difference if it had been the other way about.
He had always plenty of money nowadays.
He even had a job, a cynical more highly paid than his old job had been.
The music from the telescreen stopped and a voice took over. Winston raised his head to listen.
No bulletins from the front, however.
It was merely a brief announcement from the Ministry of Plenty.
In the preceding quarter, it appeared, the 10th Three-Year Plan's quota for
bootlesses had been over fulfilled by 98 percent He examined the chess problem and set
out the pieces. It was a tricky ending, involving a couple of nights likes to
play and mate in two moves.' Winston looked up at the portrait of Big Brother.
White always mates, he thought with a sort of cloudy mysticism.
Always, without exception, it is so arranged.
In no chess problem since the beginning of the world has black ever won.
Did it not symbolize the eternal, unvarying triumph of Good over Evil?
The huge face gazed back at him, full of calm power.
White always mates.
The voice from the telescreen paused and added in a different and much greater tone:
'You will want to stand by for an important announcement at 15 30. 1530
This is news of the highest importance.
Take care not to miss it 1530 The tinkling music struck up again.
Winston's heart stirred. That was the bulletin from the front; instinct told
him that it was bad news that was coming.
All day, with little spurts of excitement to the thought of a smashing defeat in
Africa had been in and out of his mind.
He seemed actually to see the Eurasian army swarming across the never broken
frontier and pouring down into the tip of Africa like a column of ants
or I had not been possible to outflank them in some way? The outline of the West
African coast stood out vividly in his mind.
He picked up the white knight and moved it across the board.
There was the proper spot.
Even while he saw the black horde racing southward he saw another force,
mysteriously assembled, suddenly planted in their rear, cutting their
communications by land and sea. He filtered that by willing it he was
bringing that other force into existence.
But it was necessary to act quickly.
If they could get control of the whole of Africa, if they had airfields and
submarine bases of the Cape, it would cut Oceania in two.
It might mean anything: defeat, breakdown, the re-division of the world, the
destruction of the Party!
He drew a deep breath. An extraordinary medley of feeling but it was not a
meddling exactly; rather it was successive layers of feeling, in which
one could not say which layer was undermost— —struggled inside him
spasm passed. He put the white knight back in its place, but for the moment he
could not settle down to serious study of the chess problem.
His thoughts wandered again. Almost unconsciously he traced with his finger
in the dust of the table two plus two equals five
They can't get inside you,' she had said.
But they could get inside you.
'What happens to you here is forever O'Brien had said.
That was a true word. There were things, your own acts, from which you could never recover.
Something was killed in your breast: burnt out cauterized out.
He had seen her; he had even spoken to her.
There was no danger in it. He knew as though instinctively that they now took
almost no interest in his doings.
He could have arranged to meet her a second time if either of them had wanted to.
Actually it was by chance that they had met.
It was in the Park, on a vile, biting day in March, when the earth was like iron
and all the grass seemed dead and there was not a bud anywhere except a few
crocuses Richard pushed themselves up to be dismembered by the wind.
He was hurrying along with frozen hands and watering eyes when he saw her not 10
meters away from him.
It struck him at once that she had changed in some ill-defined way.
They almost passed one another without a sign, then he turned and followed her, not
very eagerly. He knew that there was no danger, nobody would take any interest in him
She did not speak.
She walked obliquely away across the grass as though trying to get rid of him,
then seemed to resign herself to having him at her side.
Presently they were in among a clump of ragged leafless shrubs, useless either
for concealment or as protection from the wind.
They halted. It was vitally cold. The wind whistled through the twigs and fretted
the occasional dirty looking crocuses.
He put his arm around her waist.
There was no telescreen, but they must be hidden microphones: besides, they could be seen.
It did not matter, nothing mattered.
They could have laid down on the ground and done that if they had wanted to.
His flesh froze with horror as the thought of it.
She made no response whatever to the clasp of his arm; she did not even try to
disengage herself.
He knew now what had changed in her face was sallower, and there was a long scar,
partly hidden by the hair, across a foreign temple; but that was not the change.
It was that her waist had grown thicker, and, in a surprising way, had stiffened. He
remembered her once, after the explosion of a rocket bomb, he had helped to drag a
corpse out of some ruins, and had been astonished not only by the incredible
weight of the thing, but by its rigidity and awkwardness to handle, which made it
seem more like stone than flesh.
Her body felt like that. It occurred to him that the texture of her skin would
be quite different from what it once had been.
He did not attempt to kiss her, nor did they speak.
As they walked back across the grass she looked directly at him for the first time.
It was only a momentary glance, full of contempt and dislike.
He wondered whether it was a dislike that came purely out of the past or
whether it was inspired also by his bloated face and the water that the wind
kept squeezing from his eyes.
They sat down on two iron chairs, side by side but not too close together.
He saw that she was about to speak. She moved to a clumsy shoe a few centimeters
into deliberately crushed a twig.
Her feet seemed to have grown broader, he noticed.
'I betrayed you,' she said boldly I betrayed you,' he said.
She gave him another quick look of dislike. 'Sometimes,' she said, 'they threaten
you with something— —something you can't stand up to, can't even think about.
And then you say, "Don't do it to me, do it
to somebody else, do it to so and so And perhaps you might pretend, afterwards,
that it was only a trick and that you just said it to make them stop and
didn't really mean it.
But that isn't true. At the time when it happens you do mean it. You think there's
no other way of saving yourself, and you're quite ready to save yourself that way.
You wanted to happen to the other person.
You don't give a damn what they suffer.
All you care about is yourself.'
'All you care about is yourself here code And after that, you don't feel the same
towards the other person any longer.'
'No,' he said, 'you don't feel the same.'
There did not seem to be anything more to say. The wind blastered their thin
overalls against their bodies.
Almost at once it became embarrassing to sit there in silence: besides, it was too
cold to keep still.
She said something about catching her Tube and stood up to go.
'We must meet again,' he said.
'Yes,' she said, 'we must meet again.'
He followed irresolutely for a little distance, half a pace behind her.
They did not speak again.
She did not actually try to shake him off, but walked at just such a speed as
to prevent his keeping abreast of her.
He had made up his mind that he would accompany her as far as the Tube station,
but suddenly this process of trailing along in the cold seemed pointless and unbearable.
He was overwhelmed by a desire not so much to get away from Julia as to get
back to the Chestnut Tree Cafe which had never seemed so attractive as at this
moment. He had a nostalgic vision of his corner table, with the newspaper in the
chessboard and the ever flowing gin.
Above all it would be warm in there.
The next moment, not all together by accident, he allowed himself to become
separated from her by a small knot of people.
He made a half-hearted attempt to catch up, then slowed down, turned and made off
in the opposite direction.
When he had gone 50 meters he looked back. The street was not crowded, but
already he could not distinguish her.
Any one of a dozen hurrying figures might have been hers.
Perhaps her thickened, stiffened body was no longer recognizable from behind.
'At the time when it happens,' she had said,
'you do mean it.' He had meant it. He had not merely said it, he had wished it.
He had wished that she and not he should be delivered over to the———
Something changed in the music that trickled from the telescreen cracked and
jeering note, a yellow note, came into it.
And then— —perhaps it was not happening, perhaps it was only a memory taking on
the semblance of sound— —a voice was singing: Under the spreading chestnut tree I sold
you and you sold me— The tears welled up in his eyes.
A passing waiter noticed that his glass was empty and came back with the gin bottle.
He took up his glass and sniffed at it.
The stuff grew not less but more horrible with every mouthful he drank.
But it had become the element he swam in.
It was his life, his death and his resurrection.
It was gin that sank him into stupor every night, and the gin that revived him every morning.
When he woke, seldom before 1100 with gummed up eyelids and fiery mouth and a
back that seemed to be broken, it would have been impossible even to
rise from the horizontal if it had not been for the bottle and teacup placed
beside the bed overnight.
Through the midday hours he sat with glazed face, the bottle handy, listening
to the telescreen. From 15 to closing time he was a fixture in the Chestnut Tree.
No one cared what he did any longer, no whistle woke him, no telescreen admonished him.
Occasionally, perhaps twice a week, he went to a dusty forgotten looking office
in the Ministry of Truth and did a little work, or what was called work.
He had been appointed to a subcommittee of a subcommittee which had sprouted
from one of the innumerable committees dealing with minor difficulties that
arose in the compilation of the 11th Edition of the Newspeak Dictionary.
They were engaged in producing something called an Interim Report,
but what it was that they were reporting on he had never definitely found out.
It was something to do with the question of whether Commerce should be placed
inside brackets, or outside.
There were four others on the committee, all of them persons similar to himself.
There were days when they assembled and then promptly dispersed again, frankly
admitting to one another that there was not really anything to be done.
But there were other days when they settled down to their work almost
eagerly, making a tremendous show of entering up their minutes and drafting
long memoranda which were never finished— when the argument as to what they were
supposedly arguing about grew extraordinarily involved and abstruse,
with subtle haggling over definitions, enormous digressions, quarrels— —threats,
even, to appeal to higher authority.
And then suddenly the life would go out of them and they would sit around the
table looking at one another with extinct eyes, like ghosts fading at Crow
The telescreen was silent for a moment.
Winston raised his head again.
The bulletin! But no, they were merely changing the music.
He had the map of Africa behind his eyelids. The movement of the armies was a diagram:
a black arrow tearing vertically southward, and a white arrow horizontally
eastward, across the tail of the first.
As though for reassurance he looked up at the imperturbable face in the portrait.
Was it conceivable that the second arrow did not even exist?
His interest flagged again. He drank another mouthful of gin, picked up the
white knight and made a tentative move.
Check.
But it was evidently not the right move, because——— Uncalled, a memory floated into his mind.
He saw a candle-lit room with a vast white counterpaint bed, and himself, a boy
of nine or ten, sitting on the floor, shaking a dice box and laughing excitedly.
His mother was sitting opposite him and also laughing.
It must have been about a month before she disappeared. It was a moment of
reconciliation, when the nagging hunger in his belly was forgotten and his
earlier affection for her had temporarily revived.
He remembered the day well, a pelting, drenching day when the water streamed
down the window pane and the light indoors was too dull to read by.
The boredom of the two children in the dark, cramped bedroom became unbearable.
Winston whined and grizzled, made futile demands for food, fretted about the room
pulling everything out of place and kicking the wainscoting until the
neighbors banged on the wall, while the younger child wailed intermittently.
In the end his mother said, 'Now be good, and I'll buy you a toy. A lovely toy—
—you'll love it'; and then she had gone out in the rain, to a little general shop
which was still sporadically open nearby, and came back with a cardboard box
containing an outfit of Snakes and Ladders.
He could still remember the smell of the damp cardboard.
It was a miserable outfit.
The board was cracked and the tiny wooden dice were so well-cut that they
would hardly lie on their sides.
Winston looked at the thing silkily and without interest. But then his mother lit
a piece of candle and they sat down on the floor to play.
Soon he was wildly excited and shouting with laughter as the tiddlywinks climbed
hopefully up the ladders and then came slithering down the snakes again, almost
to the starting point They played eight games, winning four each.
His tiny sister, too young to understand what the game was about, had set propped
up against a bolster, laughing because the others were laughing.
For a whole afternoon they had all been happy together, as in his earlier childhood.
He pushed the picture out of his mind. It was a false memory. He was troubled by
false memories occasionally.
They did not matter so long as one knew them for what they were.
Some things had happened, others had not happened.
He turned back to the chessboard and picked up the white knight again.
Almost in the same instant it dropped on the board with a clatter. He had started
as though a pin had run into him.
A shrilled trumpet call had pierced the air. It was the bulletin! Victory! It
always meant victory when a trumpet call preceded the news.
A sort of electric drill ran through the cafe Even the waiters had started and
picked up their ears.
The trumpets call had let loose an enormous volume of noise.
.Already an excited voice was gabbling from the telescreen, but even as it
started it was almost drowned by a roar of cheering from outside.
The news had run around the streets like magic.
He could hear just enough of what was issuing from the telescreen to realize
that it had all happened as he had foreseen: a vast Seaborn armada had
secretly assembled, a sudden blow in the enemy's rear, the white arrow tearing
across the tail of the black.
Fragments of triumphant phrases pushed themselves through the din
fast strategic maneuver perfect coordination at a route half a million
prisoners— —complete demoralization control of the whole of Africa— —bring the
war within measurable distance of its end— —victory— —greatest victory in human
history— —victory, victory, victory!'
Under the table Winston's feet made convulsive movements. He had not stirred
from his seat, but in his mind he was running, swiftly running, he was with the
crowds outside, cheering himself deaf.
He looked up again at the portrait of Big Brother.
The colossus that bestowed the world!
The rock against which the hordes of Asia dashed themselves in vain!
He thought how 10 minutes ago— —yes, only 10 minutes— —there had still been
equivocation in his heart as he wondered whether the news from the front would be
a victory or defeat oh it was more than a Eurasian army that
had perished! Much had changed in him since that first day in the Ministry of
Love, but the final, indispensable, healing change had never happened, until this moment.
The voice from the telescreen was still pouring forth its tale of prisoners and
booty and slaughter, but the shouting outside had died down a little.
The waiters were turning back to their work. One of them approached with the gin bottle.
Winston, sitting in a blissful dream, paid no attention as his glass was filled up.
He was not running or cheering any longer. He was back in the Ministry of
Love, with everything forgiven, his soul whiter snow.
He was in the public dock, confessing everything, implicating everybody.
He was walking down the white-tailed corridor, with the feeling of walking in
sunlight, and an armed guard at his back.
The long hoped for bullet was entering his brain.
He gazed up at the enormous fate 40 years it had taken him to learn what
kind of smile was hidden beneath the dark mustache oh cruel, needless misunderstanding! O
stubborn, self-willed exile from the loving breast!
Two gin centered tears trickled down the sides of his nose.
But it was all right, everything was all right, the struggle was finished. He had
won the victory over himself.
He loved Big Brother.
THE END